<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="History_Table">
	<title>History Tracking</title>
	 <info>
		<abstract>
			<para>Suppose you have a table of data that represents the current state of a particular geographic feature.
			A parcels table, or a roads table, or a fruit trees table, whatever.
			Generally, GIS tools understand a table as a single entity into which they can update, insert and delete rows from.
			How you do allow common GIS tools to work against your data, while maintaining an audit trail of what changes have been made, by whom, and what the past state of the data is?</para>
			<para>This <varname>history_table</varname> extra module provides some utility functions for creating and maintaining history.</para>
		</abstract>

     </info>
     <note><para>The <varname>history_table</varname> extension is written in plpgsql and located in the <varname>extras/history_table</varname> directory of the PostGIS source tree.</para></note>
     <para>If you have a table 'roads', this module will maintain a 'roads_history' side table, which contains all the columns of the parent table, and the following additional columns:</para>
<programlisting>history_id      | integer                     | not null default
 date_added      | timestamp without time zone | not null default now()
 date_deleted    | timestamp without time zone |
 last_operation  | character varying(30)       | not null
 active_user     | character varying(90)       | not null default "current_user"()
 current_version | text                        | not null</programlisting>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
	<para>When you insert a new record into 'roads' a record is automatically inserted into 'roads_history', with the 'date_added' filled in the 'date_deleted' set to NULL, a unique 'history_id', a 'last_operation' of 'INSERT' and 'active_user' set.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
	<para>When you delete a record in 'roads', the record in the history table is *not* deleted, but the 'date_deleted' is set to the current date.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
	<para>When you update a record in 'roads', the current record has 'date_deleted' filled in and a new record is created with the 'date_added' set and 'date_deleted' NULL.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>With this information maintained, it is possible to retrieve the history of any record in the roads table:</para>
<programlisting>SELECT * FROM roads_history WHERE roads_pk = 111;</programlisting>

<para>Or, to retrieve a view of the roads table at any point in the past:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT * FROM roads_history
    WHERE date_added < 'January 1, 2001' AND
        ( date_deleted >= 'January 1, 2001' OR date_deleted IS NULL );
]]></programlisting>

        &ref_extras_historytable_Postgis_Install_History;

		&ref_extras_historytable_Postgis_Enable_History;
</section>
