<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xml:id="Topology"
>
	<title>Topology</title>
	<para>The PostGIS Topology types and functions are used to manage topological objects such as faces, edges and nodes. </para>
	<para>Sandro Santilli's presentation at PostGIS Day Paris 2011  conference gives a good synopsis of PostGIS Topology and where it is headed <link xlink:href="http://strk.kbt.io/projects/postgis/Paris2011_TopologyWithPostGIS_2_0.pdf">Topology with PostGIS 2.0 slide deck</link>.</para>
	<para>
Vincent Picavet provides a good synopsis and overview of what is Topology,
how is it used, and various FOSS4G tools that support it in <link xlink:href="https://gitlab.com/Oslandia/documentation/presentations/-/blob/master/2012/pgconf_eu_2012/pgconfeu2012_vincent_picavet_postgis_topology.pdf">PostGIS Topology PGConf EU 2012</link>.
    </para>
    <para>An example of a topologically based GIS database is the <link xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger.html">US Census Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing System (TIGER)</link> database. If you want to experiment with PostGIS topology and need some data.</para>
	<para>The PostGIS topology module has existed for a long time but was not always part of the official documentation.
	    Extensive cleanup removed deprecated functions, fixed known usability issues, documented the features and functions, added new functionality, and improved SQL-MM compliance.</para>
	<para>Details of this project can be found at <link xlink:href="http://trac.osgeo.org/postgis/wiki/UsersWikiPostgisTopology">PostGIS Topology Wiki</link></para>
	<para>All functions and tables associated with this module are installed in a schema called <varname>topology</varname>.</para>
	<para>Functions that are defined in SQL/MM standard are prefixed with ST_ and functions specific to PostGIS are not prefixed.</para>
        <para>Topology support is built by default and can be disabled by specifying the --without-topology configure option at build time as described in <xref linkend="postgis_installation"/></para>

        <section xml:id="Topology_PrimitiveTables">
            <title>Topology Primitive Tables</title>
            <para>The core primitives of any topology are stored in the <varname>edge_data</varname>, <varname>node</varname>, and <varname>face</varname> tables that live in the schema created by <xref linkend="CreateTopology"/>.  Each row of <varname>edge_data</varname> represents an oriented edge: it records a directed curve from <varname>start_node</varname> to <varname>end_node</varname> together with the identifier of the face encountered on the left of that direction (<varname>left_face</varname>) and the face encountered on the right (<varname>right_face</varname>).  The same geometric segment may therefore appear twice—once for each orientation—when it belongs to two faces.</para>
            <para>The <varname>next_left_edge</varname> and <varname>next_right_edge</varname> columns complete this orientation information by encoding how to keep walking around a face.  They store signed integers whose absolute value is the identifier of the next oriented edge and whose sign determines whether the stored orientation has to be followed as-is or reversed when traversing.  Formally, the following rules hold for every edge <varname>e</varname>:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><varname>abs(next_left_edge)</varname> is the identifier of the edge reached by continuing around the face that lies to the left of <varname>e</varname>.  If the value is positive the walk continues from the end node of <varname>e</varname> along the stored orientation of the referenced edge; if it is negative the referenced edge must be followed backwards so that the shared face remains on the walker’s left.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><varname>abs(next_right_edge)</varname> analogously follows the boundary of the face located on the right of <varname>e</varname>.  A positive value means that the next edge is taken with its recorded orientation starting from the end node of <varname>e</varname>, whereas a negative value instructs to traverse the referenced edge in reverse, starting from its end node, so that the right-hand face is preserved.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A zero value indicates that the edge is dangling on the corresponding side (for example an isolated edge whose incident face is the universal face <varname>0</varname>).  The <varname>abs_next_left_edge</varname> and <varname>abs_next_right_edge</varname> columns exposed by the <varname>edge</varname> view are convenience projections of these absolute values.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>This representation is a variant of a doubly connected edge list and is exploited by many topology routines.  Functions such as <xref linkend="GetRingEdges"/> and <xref linkend="ValidateTopology"/> rely on it to reconstruct face boundaries and to diagnose inconsistencies—hence the “invalid next_left_edge” and “invalid next_right_edge” diagnostics reported during validation.  Constructors like <xref linkend="AddEdge"/> initialise the <varname>next_*</varname> attributes with trivial self references, while editing routines including <xref linkend="ST_AddEdgeModFace"/> and <xref linkend="ST_RemEdgeModFace"/> update the links as edges are inserted or removed.  Other bulk operations (for example <xref linkend="TopologyPolygonize"/>) may intentionally leave the fields unset, which is why the documentation flags their behaviour explicitly.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="Topology_Types">
        <title>Topology Types</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>This section lists the PostgreSQL data types installed by PostGIS Topology.  Note we describe the casting behavior of these which is very
                    important especially when designing your own functions.
                </para>
            </abstract>
        </info>


		&ref_extras_topology_getfaceedges_returntype;

		&ref_extras_topology_topogeometry;

		&ref_extras_topology_validatetopology_returntype;
	</section>

	<section xml:id="Topology_Domains">
        <title>Topology Domains</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>This section lists the PostgreSQL domains installed by PostGIS Topology.  Domains can be used like object types as return objects of functions or table columns. The distinction between
                    a domain and a type is that a domain is an existing type with a check constraint bound to it.
                </para>
            </abstract>
        </info>


		&ref_extras_topology_topoelement;

		&ref_extras_topology_topoelementarray;
	</section>

	<section xml:id="Topology_ManagementFunctions">
	     <title>Topology and TopoGeometry Management</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>This section lists the Topology functions for building new Topology schemas, validating topologies, and managing TopoGeometry Columns</para>
            </abstract>
        </info>

	    &ref_extras_topology_AddTopoGeometryColumn;
	    &ref_extras_topology_RenameTopoGeometryColumn;
		&ref_extras_topology_DropTopology;
		&ref_extras_topology_RenameTopology;
		&ref_extras_topology_DropTopoGeometryColumn;

        &ref_extras_topology_FixCorruptTopoGeometryColumn;

		&ref_extras_topology_Populate_Topology_Layer;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopologySummary;

		&ref_extras_topology_ValidateTopology;

		&ref_extras_topology_ValidateTopologyRelation;

		&ref_extras_topology_ValidateTopologyPrecision;

		&ref_extras_topology_MakeTopologyPrecise;

		&ref_extras_topology_FindTopology;

		&ref_extras_topology_FindLayer;

		&ref_extras_topology_TotalTopologySize;

        &ref_extras_topology_UpgradeTopology;
	</section>

	<section xml:id="Topology_StatsManagement" xreflabel="maintaining statistics during topology editing and population">
	     <title>Topology Statistics Management</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>
This section discusses management of database statistics during
topology building.
                </para>
            </abstract>
        </info>


<para>
Adding elements to a topology triggers many database queries for
finding existing edges that will be split, adding nodes and
updating edges that will node with the new linework. For this reason
it is useful that statistics about the data in the topology tables
are up-to-date.
</para>

<para>
PostGIS Topology population and editing functions do not automatically
update the statistics because a updating stats after each and every
change in a topology would be overkill, so it is the caller's duty
to take care of that.
</para>

<note>
<para>
That the statistics updated by autovacuum
will NOT be visible to transactions which started before autovacuum
process completed, so long-running transactions will need to run
ANALYZE themselves, to use updated statistics.
</para>
</note>

	</section>

	<section xml:id="Topology_Constructors">
    <title>Topology Constructors</title><info>
        <abstract>
            <para>This section covers the topology functions for creating new topologies.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>


		&ref_extras_topology_CreateTopology;

		&ref_extras_topology_CopyTopology;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_InitTopoGeo;


		&ref_extras_topology_ST_CreateTopoGeo;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopoGeo_AddPoint;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopoGeo_AddLineString;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopoGeo_AddPolygon;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopoGeo_LoadGeometry;


	</section>

	<section xml:id="Topology_Editing">
	    <title>Topology Editors</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>This section covers topology functions for adding, moving, deleting, and splitting edges, faces, and nodes. All of these functions are defined by ISO SQL/MM.</para>
            </abstract>
        </info>


		&ref_extras_topology_ST_AddIsoNode;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_AddIsoEdge;

		  &ref_extras_topology_ST_AddEdgeNewFaces;

		  &ref_extras_topology_ST_AddEdgeModFace;

    &ref_extras_topology_ST_RemEdgeNewFace;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_RemEdgeModFace;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_ChangeEdgeGeom;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_ModEdgeSplit;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_ModEdgeHeal;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_NewEdgeHeal;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_MoveIsoNode;
		  &ref_extras_topology_ST_NewEdgesSplit;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_RemoveIsoNode;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_RemoveIsoEdge;
	</section>


	<section xml:id="Topology_Accessors">
	  <title>Topology Accessors</title>
        &ref_extras_topology_GetEdgeByPoint;

        &ref_extras_topology_GetFaceByPoint;

        &ref_extras_topology_GetFaceContainingPoint;

        &ref_extras_topology_GetNodeByPoint;

		&ref_extras_topology_GetTopologyID;

		&ref_extras_topology_GetTopologySRID;

		&ref_extras_topology_GetTopologyName;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_GetFaceEdges;

		&ref_extras_topology_ST_GetFaceGeometry;

		&ref_extras_topology_GetRingEdges;

		&ref_extras_topology_GetNodeEdges;

		&ref_extras_topology_FindVertexSegmentPairsBelowDistance;

	</section>


	<section xml:id="Topology_Processing">
    <title>Topology Processing</title><info>
        <abstract>
            <para>This section covers the functions for processing topologies in non-standard ways.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>

		&ref_extras_topology_TopologyPolygonize;

		&ref_extras_topology_AddNode;

	     &ref_extras_topology_AddEdge;

		&ref_extras_topology_AddFace;

	&ref_extras_topology_TP_ST_Simplify;

	&ref_extras_topology_TP_RemoveUnusedPrimitives;


	</section>

	<section xml:id="TopoGeometry_Constructors">
    <title>TopoGeometry Constructors</title><info>
        <abstract>
            <para>This section covers the topology functions for creating new topogeometries.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>

		&ref_extras_topology_CreateTopoGeom;

		&ref_extras_topology_toTopoGeom;

		&ref_extras_topology_TopoElementArray_Agg;

        &ref_extras_topology_TopoElement;
	</section>

	<section xml:id="TopoGeometry_Editors">
    <title>TopoGeometry Editors</title><info>
        <abstract>
            <para>This section covers the topology functions for editing existing topogeometries.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>


		&ref_extras_topology_clearTopoGeom;

    &ref_extras_topology_TopoGeom_addElement;

    &ref_extras_topology_TopoGeom_remElement;

    &ref_extras_topology_TopoGeom_addTopoGeom;

    &ref_extras_topology_toTopoGeom_editor_proxy;


	</section>

	<section xml:id="TopoGeom_Accessors">
	  <title>TopoGeometry Accessors</title>

	      &ref_extras_topology_GetTopoGeomElementArray;
		&ref_extras_topology_GetTopoGeomElements;

    &ref_extras_topology_TG_ST_SRID;

	</section>


	<section xml:id="TopoGeometry_Outputs">
	  <title>TopoGeometry Outputs</title>
	  &ref_extras_topology_AsGML;
	  &ref_extras_topology_AsTopoJSON;
</section>

<section xml:id="Topology_Relationships">
	     <title>Topology Spatial Relationships</title><info>
            <abstract>
                <para>This section lists the Topology functions used to check relationships between topogeometries and topology primitives</para>
            </abstract>
        </info>

	    &ref_extras_topology_TG_Equals;

      &ref_extras_topology_TG_Intersects;
</section>

<section xml:id="Topology_Import_Export">
    <title>Importing and exporting Topologies</title>

    <para>
Once you have created topologies, and maybe associated topological layers,
you might want to export them into a file-based format for backup or transfer
into another database.
    </para>

    <para>
Using the standard dump/restore tools of PostgreSQL is
problematic because topologies are composed by a set of tables (4 for
primitives, an arbitrary number for layers) and records in metadata tables
(topology.topology and topology.layer). Additionally, topology identifiers
are not univoque across databases so that parameter of your topology
will need to be changes upon restoring it.
    </para>

    <para>
In order to simplify export/restore of topologies a pair of
executables are provided: <filename>pgtopo_export</filename>
and <filename>pgtopo_import</filename>. Example usage:
    </para>
<programlisting>
pgtopo_export dev_db topo1 | pgtopo_import topo1 | psql staging_db
</programlisting>

    <section xml:id="pgtopo_export">
        <title>Using the Topology exporter</title>

        <para>
The <filename>pgtopo_export</filename> script takes the name of a
database and a topology and outputs a dump file which can be used
to import the topology (and associated layers) into a new database.
        </para>

        <para>
By default <filename>pgtopo_export</filename> writes the
dump file to the standard output so that it can be piped to
<filename>pgtopo_import</filename> or redirected to a file
(refusing to write to terminal). You can optionally specify
an output filename with the <code>-f</code> commandline switch.
        </para>

        <para>
By default <filename>pgtopo_export</filename> includes a dump
of all layers defined against the given topology. This may be more
data than you need, or may be non-working (in case your layer tables
have complex dependencies) in which case you can request skipping the
layers with the <code>--skip-layers</code> switch and deal with those
separately.
        </para>

        <para>
Invoking <filename>pgtopo_export</filename> with the
<code>--help</code> (or <code>-h</code> for short) switch
will always print short usage string.
        </para>


        <para>
The dump file format is a compressed tar archive of a
<filename>pgtopo_export</filename> directory containing
at least a <filename>pgtopo_dump_version</filename> file with
format version info. As of version <code>1</code> the directory
contains tab-delimited CSV files with data of the topology
primitive tables (node, edge_data, face, relation), the
topology and layer records associated with it and
(unless <code>--skip-layers</code> is given) a custom-format
PostgreSQL dump of tables reported as being layers of the given
topology.
        </para>

    </section> <!-- pgtopo_export -->

    <section xml:id="pgtopo_import">
        <title>Using the Topology importer</title>

        <para>
The <filename>pgtopo_import</filename> script takes a
<code>pgtopo_export</code> format topology dump and a
name to give to  the topology to be created and outputs
an SQL script reconstructing the topology and associated
layers.
        </para>

        <para>
The generated SQL file will contain statements that create
a topology with the given name, load primitive data in it,
restores and registers all topology layers by properly
linking all TopoGeometry values to their correct topology.
        </para>


        <para>
By default <filename>pgtopo_import</filename> reads the dump
from the standard input so that it can be used in conjunction
with <filename>pgtopo_export</filename> in a pipeline.
You can optionally specify an input filename with the
<code>-f</code> commandline switch.
        </para>

        <para>
By default <filename>pgtopo_import</filename> includes in the output
SQL file the code to restore all layers found in the dump.
        </para>

        <para>
This may be unwanted or non-working in case your target database already
have tables with the same name as the ones in the dump. In that case
you can request skipping the layers with the <code>--skip-layers</code>
switch and deal with those separately (or later).
        </para>

        <para>
SQL to only load and link layers to a named topology can be generated
using the <code>--only-layers</code> switch. This can be useful to load
layers AFTER resolving the naming conflicts or to link layers to a
different topology (say a spatially-simplified version of the starting
topology).
        </para>

        <para>
If the target topology already exists and you want it dropped upfront
you can pass the <code>--drop-topology</code> switch (since PostGIS-3.6.0).
        </para>

    </section> <!-- pgtopo_import -->

</section> <!-- Importing and exporting Topologies -->

</chapter>
