<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>
    This chapter details the steps required to install PostGIS.
  </para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Short Version</title>

    <programlisting>tar xvfz postgis-@@LAST_RELEASE_VERSION@@.tar.gz
cd postgis-@@LAST_RELEASE_VERSION@@
./configure
make
make install
createlang plpgsql yourdatabase
psql -d yourdatabase -f lwpostgis.sql
psql -d yourdatabase -f spatial_ref_sys.sql</programlisting>

    <para>
      The rest of this chapter goes into detail each of the above installation
      steps.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      PostGIS has the following requirements for building and usage:
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          PostgreSQL 8.1 or higher. A complete installation of PostgreSQL
          (including server headers) is required. PostgreSQL is available from
          <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org">
            http://www.postgresql.org
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GNU C compiler (<filename>gcc</filename>). Some other ANSI C compilers
          can be used to compile PostGIS, but we find far fewer problems when
          compiling with <filename>gcc</filename>.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GNU Make (<filename>gmake</filename> or <filename>make</filename>).
          For many systems, GNU <filename>make</filename> is the default version
          of make. Check the version by invoking <filename>make -v</filename>.
          Other versions of <filename>make</filename> may not process the
          PostGIS <filename>Makefile</filename> properly.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Proj4 reprojection library. The Proj4 library is used to provide
          coordinate reprojection support within PostGIS. Proj4 is available for
          download from
          <ulink url="http://trac.osgeo.org/proj/">
            http://trac.osgeo.org/proj/
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GEOS geometry library. The GEOS library is used to provide geometry
          tests (ST_Touches(), ST_Contains(), ST_Intersects()) and operations
          (ST_Buffer(), ST_Union(), ST_Difference()) within PostGIS. GEOS is
          available for download from
          <ulink url="http://trac.osgeo.org/geos/">
            http://trac.osgeo.org/geos/
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Apache Ant (<filename>ant</filename>) is required for building any of
          the drivers under the <filename>java</filename> directory. Ant is
          available from
          <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org">
            http://ant.apache.org
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          DocBook (<filename>xsltproc</filename>) is required for building the
          documentation. Docbook is available from
          <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/">
            http://www.docbook.org/
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          DBLatex (<filename>dblatex</filename>) is required for building the
          documentation in PDF format. DBLatex is available from
          <ulink url="http://dblatex.sourceforge.net/">
            http://dblatex.sourceforge.net/
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          ImageMagick (<filename>convert</filename>) is required to generate the
          images used in the documentation. ImageMagick is available from
          <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/">
            http://www.imagemagick.org/
          </ulink>
          .
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="PGInstall">
    <title>PostGIS</title>

    <para>
      The PostGIS module is an extension to the PostgreSQL backend server. As
      such, PostGIS &last_release_version; <emphasis>requires</emphasis> full
      PostgreSQL server headers access in order to compile. The PostgreSQL
      source code is available at
      <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org">
        http://www.postgresql.org
      </ulink>
      .
    </para>

    <para>
      PostGIS &last_release_version; can be built against PostgreSQL versions
      8.1.0 or higher. Earlier versions of PostgreSQL are
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Many OS systems now include pre-built packages for PostgreSQL/PostGIS.
        In many cases compilation is only necessary if you want the most
        bleeding edge versions or you are a package maintainer.
      </para>
    </note>

    <note>
      <para>
        If you would like to compile your own, more specific instructions for
        <ulink url="http://trac.osgeo.org/postgis/wiki/UsersWikiWinCompile">
          Windows Compiling Guide
        </ulink>
        and others are available in
        <ulink url="http://trac.osgeo.org/postgis/wiki/UsersWikiMain">
          PostGIS User Wiki
        </ulink>
      </para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="firsttimeinstall">
      <title>Compiling and Installing from Source</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Before you can compile the PostGIS server modules, you must compile
            and install the PostgreSQL package.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              For GEOS functionality you might need to explicitly link
              PostgreSQL against the standard C++ library:
            </para>

            <programlisting>LDFLAGS=-lstdc++ ./configure [YOUR OPTIONS HERE]</programlisting>

            <para>
              This is a workaround for bogus C++ exceptions interaction with
              older development tools. If you experience weird problems (backend
              unexpectedly closed or similar things) try this trick. This will
              require recompiling your PostgreSQL from scratch, of course.
            </para>

            <para>
              The steps that follow are for Linux users. They will not work on
              Windows or Mac
            </para>

            <para>
              For the below - if you are not logged in as root, you may need to
              use sudo or su commands to run the make make install commands
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Retrieve the PostGIS source archive from
            <ulink url="http://postgis.refractions.net/download/postgis-&last_release_version;.tar.gz">
              http://postgis.refractions.net/download/postgis-&last_release_version;.tar.gz
            </ulink>
            . Uncompress and untar the archive. configure.
          </para>

          <para>
            All files are installed using information provided by
            <filename>pg_config</filename>
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Libraries are installed
                <filename>[pkglibdir]/lib/contrib</filename>.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                Important support files such as <filename>postgis.sql</filename>
                are installed in <filename>[prefix]/share/contrib</filename>.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                Loader and dumper binaries are installed in
                <filename>[bindir]/</filename>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <programlisting>wget http://postgis.refractions.net/download/postgis-&last_release_version;.tar.gz
gzip -d -c postgis-&last_release_version;.tar.gz | tar xvf -
cd postgis-&last_release_version;/
./configure</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Make and Install
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                PostgreSQL provides a utility called
                <filename>pg_config</filename> to enable extensions like PostGIS
                to locate the PostgreSQL installation directory. If ./configure
                didn't find <filename>pg_config</filename>, try using the
                <code>--with-pgconfig=/path/to/pg_config</code> switch to
                specify a particular PostgreSQL installation.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                Proj4 is now required in order to build and use PostGIS. If
                ./configure didn't find the Proj4 library, try using the
                <code>--with-projdir=/path/to/projdir</code> switch to specify
                an alternative Proj4 installation directory. If you have not
                compiled or installed Proj4, follow the instructions below if
                you wish to compile Proj4 from source.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                GEOS is now required in order to build and use PostGIS. If
                ./configure didn't find it, try using the
                <code>--with-geosconfig=/path/to/geos-config</code> switch to
                specify the full path to the <filename>geos-config</filename>
                program. If you have not compiled or installed Geos, follow the
                instructions that follow below to compile Geos from source.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <programlisting>make clean &amp;&amp; make
make install
ldconfig</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you are missing proj based on above or running a version below
            4.5, then install by following these steps.
          </para>

          <programlisting>wget http://download.osgeo.org/proj/proj-&last_proj_release_version;.tar.gz
gzip -d -c proj-&last_proj_release_version;.tar.gz | tar xvf -
cd proj-&last_proj_release_version;
./configure &amp;&amp; make clean &amp;&amp; make
make install
ldconfig
cd ..</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you are missing geos based on above or running a version below
            3.0, then install by following these steps.
          </para>

          <programlisting>wget http://download.osgeo.org/geos/geos-&last_geos_release_version;.tar.bz2
bunzip2 -d -c geos-&last_geos_release_version;.tar.bz2 | tar xvf -
cd geos-&last_geos_release_version;
./configure &amp;&amp; make clean &amp;&amp; make
make install
ldconfig
cd ..</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            PostGIS requires the PL/pgSQL procedural language extension. Before
            loading the <filename>postgis.sql</filename> file, you must first
            enable PL/pgSQL. You should use the <filename>createlang</filename>
            command. The PostgreSQL Programmer's Guide has the details if you
            want to this manually for some reason.
          </para>

          <programlisting># createlang plpgsql [yourdatabase]</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Now load the PostGIS object and function definitions into your
            database by loading the <filename>postgis.sql</filename> definitions
            file.
          </para>

          <programlisting># psql -d [yourdatabase] -f lwgeom/postgis.sql</programlisting>

          <para>
            The PostGIS server extensions are now loaded and ready to use.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            For a complete set of EPSG coordinate system definition identifiers,
            you can also load the <filename>spatial_ref_sys.sql</filename>
            definitions file and populate the <varname>SPATIAL_REF_SYS</varname>
            table.
          </para>

          <programlisting># psql -d [yourdatabase] -f spatial_ref_sys.sql</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="templatepostgis">
      <title>Creating PostGIS spatially-enabled databases from an in-built
	  template</title>

      <para>
        Some packaged distributions of PostGIS (in particular the Win32
        installers for PostGIS &gt;= 1.1.5) load the PostGIS functions into a
        template database called <varname>template_postgis</varname>. If the
        <varname>template_postgis</varname> database exists in your PostgreSQL
        installation then it is possible for users and/or applications to create
        spatially-enabled databases using a single command. Note that in both
        cases, the database user must have been granted the privilege to create
        new databases.
      </para>

      <para>
        From the shell:
      </para>

      <programlisting># createdb -T template_postgis my_spatial_db</programlisting>

      <para>
        From SQL:
      </para>

      <programlisting>postgres=# CREATE DATABASE my_spatial_db TEMPLATE=template_postgis</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="upgrading">
      <title>Upgrading</title>

      <para>
        Upgrading existing spatial databases can be tricky as it requires
        replacement or introduction of new PostGIS object definitions.
      </para>

      <para>
        Unfortunately not all definitions can be easily replaced in a live
        database, so sometimes your best bet is a dump/reload process.
      </para>

      <para>
        PostGIS provides a SOFT UPGRADE procedure for minor or bugfix releases,
        and an HARD UPGRADE procedure for major releases.
      </para>

      <para>
        Before attempting to upgrade postgis, it is always worth to backup your
        data. If you use the -Fc flag to pg_dump you will always be able to
        restore the dump with an HARD UPGRADE.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="soft_upgrade">
        <title>Soft upgrade</title>

        <para>
          Soft upgrade consists of sourcing the postgis_upgrade.sql script in
          your spatial database:
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ psql -f postgis_upgrade.sql -d your_spatial_database</programlisting>

        <para>
          If a soft upgrade is not possible the script will abort and you will
          be warned about HARD UPGRADE being required, so do not hesitate to try
          a soft upgrade first.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            If you can't find the <filename>postgis_upgrade.sql</filename> file
            you are probably using a version prior to 1.1 and must generate that
            file by yourself. This is done with the following command:
          </para>

          <programlisting>$ utils/postgis_proc_upgrade.pl postgis.sql &gt; postgis_upgrade.sql</programlisting>
        </note>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="hard_upgrade">
        <title>Hard upgrade</title>

        <para>
          By HARD UPGRADE we intend full dump/reload of postgis-enabled
          databases. You need an HARD UPGRADE when postgis objects' internal
          storage changes or when SOFT UPGRADE is not possible. The
          <link linkend="release_notes">Release Notes</link>
          appendix reports for each version whether you need a dump/reload (HARD
          UPGRADE) to upgrade.
        </para>

        <para>
          PostGIS provides an utility script to restore a dump produced with the
          pg_dump -Fc command. It is experimental so redirecting its output to a
          file will help in case of problems. The procedure is as follow:
        </para>

        <para>
          Create a "custom-format" dump of the database you want to upgrade
          (let's call it "olddb")
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ pg_dump -Fc olddb &gt; olddb.dump</programlisting>

        <para>
          Restore the dump contextually upgrading postgis into a new database.
          The new database doesn't have to exist. postgis_restore accepts
          createdb parameters after the dump file name, and that can for
          instance be used if you are using a non-default character encoding for
          your database. Let's call it "newdb", with UNICODE as the character
          encoding:
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ sh utils/postgis_restore.pl postgis.sql newdb olddb.dump -E=UNICODE &gt; restore.log</programlisting>

        <para>
          Check that all restored dump objects really had to be restored from
          dump and do not conflict with the ones defined in postgis.sql
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ grep ^KEEPING restore.log | less</programlisting>

        <para>
          If upgrading from PostgreSQL &lt; 8.0 to &gt;= 8.0 you might want to
          drop the attrelid, varattnum and stats columns in the geometry_columns
          table, which are no-more needed. Keeping them won't hurt. DROPPING
          THEM WHEN REALLY NEEDED WILL DO HURT !
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ psql newdb -c "ALTER TABLE geometry_columns DROP attrelid"
$ psql newdb -c "ALTER TABLE geometry_columns DROP varattnum"
$ psql newdb -c "ALTER TABLE geometry_columns DROP stats"</programlisting>

        <para>
          spatial_ref_sys table is restore from the dump, to ensure your custom
          additions are kept, but the distributed one might contain modification
          so you should backup your entries, drop the table and source the new
          one. If you did make additions we assume you know how to backup them
          before upgrading the table. Replace of it with the new one is done
          like this:
        </para>

        <programlisting>$ psql newdb
newdb=&gt; drop spatial_ref_sys;
DROP
newdb=&gt; \i spatial_ref_sys.sql</programlisting>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Common Problems</title>

      <para>
        There are several things to check when your installation or upgrade
        doesn't go as you expected.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Check that you you have installed PostgreSQL 8.1 or newer, and that
            you are compiling against the same version of the PostgreSQL source
            as the version of PostgreSQL that is running. Mix-ups can occur when
            your (Linux) distribution has already installed PostgreSQL, or you
            have otherwise installed PostgreSQL before and forgotten about it.
            PostGIS will only work with PostgreSQL 8.1 or newer, and strange,
            unexpected error messages will result if you use an older version.
            To check the version of PostgreSQL which is running, connect to the
            database using psql and run this query:
          </para>

          <programlisting>SELECT version();</programlisting>

          <para>
            If you are running an RPM based distribution, you can check for the
            existence of pre-installed packages using the <command>rpm</command>
            command as follows: <command>rpm -qa | grep postgresql</command>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        Also check that configure has correctly detected the location and
        version of PostgreSQL, the Proj4 library and the GEOS library.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The output from configure is used to generate the
            <filename>postgis_config.h</filename> file. Check that the
            <varname>POSTGIS_PGSQL_VERSION</varname>,
            <varname>POSTGIS_PROJ_VERSION</varname> and
            <varname>POSTGIS_GEOS_VERSION</varname> variables have been set
            correctly.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>JDBC</title>

    <para>
      The JDBC extensions provide Java objects corresponding to the internal
      PostGIS types. These objects can be used to write Java clients which query
      the PostGIS database and draw or do calculations on the GIS data in
      PostGIS.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Enter the <filename>java/jdbc</filename> sub-directory of the PostGIS
          distribution.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Run the <filename>ant</filename> command. Copy the
          <filename>postgis.jar</filename> file to wherever you keep your java
          libraries.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      The JDBC extensions require a PostgreSQL JDBC driver to be present in the
      current CLASSPATH during the build process. If the PostgreSQL JDBC driver
      is located elsewhere, you may pass the location of the JDBC driver JAR
      separately using the -D parameter like this:
    </para>

    <programlisting># ant -Dclasspath=/path/to/postgresql-jdbc.jar</programlisting>

    <para>
      PostgreSQL JDBC drivers can be downloaded from
      <ulink url="http://jdbc.postgresql.org">
        http://jdbc.postgresql.org
      </ulink>
      .
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Loader/Dumper</title>

    <para>
      The data loader and dumper are built and installed automatically as part
      of the PostGIS build. To build and install them manually:
    </para>

    <programlisting># cd postgis-&last_release_version;/loader
# make
# make install</programlisting>

    <para>
      The loader is called <filename>shp2pgsql</filename> and converts ESRI
      Shape files into SQL suitable for loading in PostGIS/PostgreSQL. The
      dumper is called <filename>pgsql2shp</filename> and converts PostGIS
      tables (or queries) into ESRI Shape files. For more verbose documentation,
      see the online help, and the manual pages.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
