<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>PostGIS is developed by Refractions Research Inc, as a spatial
  database technology research project. Refractions is a GIS and database
  consulting company in Victoria, British Columbia, Canada, specializing in
  data integration and custom software development. We plan on supporting and
  developing PostGIS to support a range of important GIS functionality,
  including full OpenGIS support, advanced topological constructs (coverages,
  surfaces, networks), desktop user interface tools for viewing and editing
  GIS data, and web-based access tools.</para>

  <sect1 id="credits">
    <title>Credits</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sandro Santilli &lt;strk@refractions.net&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Coordinates all bug fixing and maintenance effort, integration
          of new GEOS functionality, and new function enhancements.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mark Leslie &lt;mleslie@refractions.net&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ongoing maintenance and development of core functions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Chris Hodgson &lt;chodgson@refractions.net&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maintains new functions and the 7.2 index bindings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Paul Ramsey &lt;pramsey@refractions.net&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Keeps track of the documentation and packaging.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Jeff Lounsbury &lt;jeffloun@refractions.net&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Original development of the Shape file loader/dumper.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dave Blasby &lt;dblasby@gmail.com&gt;</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The original developer of PostGIS. Dave wrote the server side
          objects, index bindings, and many of the server side analytical
          functions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Other contributors</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>In alphabetical order: Alex Bodnaru, Alex Mayrhofer, Bruce
          Rindahl, Bernhard Reiter, Bruno Wolff III, Carl Anderson, Charlie
          Savage, David Skea, David Techer, IIDA Tetsushi, Geographic Data BC,
          Gerald Fenoy, Gino Lucrezi, Klaus Foerster, Kris Jurka, Mark
          Cave-Ayland, Mark Sondheim, Markus Schaber, Michael Fuhr, Nikita
          Shulga, Norman Vine, Olivier Courtin, Ralph Mason, Steffen
          Macke.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Important Support Libraries</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <ulink url="http://geos.refractions.net">GEOS</ulink>
          geometry operations library, and the algorithmic work of Martin
          Davis &lt;mbdavis@vividsolutions.com&gt; of Vivid Solutions in
          making it all work.</para>

          <para>The <ulink url="http://proj4.maptools.org">Proj4</ulink>
          cartographic projection library, and the work of Gerald Evenden and
          Frank Warmerdam in creating and maintaining it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>More Information</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The latest software, documentation and news items are available
        at the PostGIS web site, <ulink
        url="http://postgis.refractions.net">http://postgis.refractions.net</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More information about the GEOS geometry operations library is
        available at<ulink url="http://geos.refractions.net">
        http://geos.refractions.net</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More information about the Proj4 reprojection library is
        available at <ulink
        url="http://www.remotesensing.org/proj">http://www.remotesensing.org/proj</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More information about the PostgreSQL database server is
        available at the PostgreSQL main site <ulink
        url="http://www.postgresql.org">http://www.postgresql.org</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More information about GiST indexing is available at the
        PostgreSQL GiST development site, <ulink
        url="http://www.sai.msu.su/~megera/postgres/gist">http://www.sai.msu.su/~megera/postgres/gist</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More information about Mapserver internet map server is
        available at <ulink
        url="http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/">http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The "<ulink url="http://www.opengis.org/docs/99-049.pdf">Simple
        Features for Specification for SQL</ulink>" is available at the
        OpenGIS Consortium web site: <ulink
        url="http://www.opengis.org">http://www.opengis.org</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>