<refentry xml:id="ST_FilterByM" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
      <refnamediv>
        <refname>ST_FilterByM</refname>
        <refpurpose>Removes vertices based on their M value</refpurpose>
      </refnamediv>

      <refsynopsisdiv>
        <funcsynopsis>
          <funcprototype>
            <funcdef>geometry <function>ST_FilterByM</function></funcdef>
            <paramdef><type>geometry</type> <parameter>geom</parameter></paramdef>
            <paramdef><type>double precision</type> <parameter>min</parameter></paramdef>
            <paramdef><type>double precision</type> <parameter>max = null</parameter></paramdef>
            <paramdef><type>boolean</type> <parameter>returnM = false</parameter></paramdef>
          </funcprototype>
        </funcsynopsis>
      </refsynopsisdiv>

      <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>Filters out vertex points based on their M-value. Returns a geometry with only
            vertex points that have a M-value larger or equal to the min value and smaller or equal to
            the max value. If max-value argument is left out only min value is considered. If fourth argument is left out the m-value
            will not be in the resulting geometry. If resulting geometry have too few vertex points left for its geometry type an empty
            geometry will be returned. In a geometry collection
            geometries without enough points will just be left out silently.</para>
        <para>This function is mainly intended to be used in conjunction with ST_SetEffectiveArea. ST_EffectiveArea sets the effective area
            of a vertex in its m-value. With ST_FilterByM it then is possible to get a simplified version of the geometry without any calculations, just by filtering</para>

        <note><para>There is a difference in what ST_SimplifyVW returns when not enough points meet the criteria compared to ST_FilterByM.
                ST_SimplifyVW returns the geometry with enough points while ST_FilterByM returns an empty geometry</para></note>
        <note><para>Note that the returned geometry might be invalid</para></note>
        <note><para>This function returns all dimensions, including the Z and M values</para></note>
        <para role="availability" conformance="2.5.0">Availability: 2.5.0</para>
      </refsection>

          <refsection>
            <title>Examples</title>
            <para>A linestring is filtered</para>
                <programlisting>
SELECT ST_AsText(ST_FilterByM(geom,30)) simplified
FROM (SELECT  ST_SetEffectiveArea('LINESTRING(5 2, 3 8, 6 20, 7 25, 10 10)'::geometry) geom) As foo;
<lineannotation>
result
</lineannotation>
         simplified
----------------------------
 LINESTRING(5 2,7 25,10 10)
                </programlisting>
          </refsection>
          <refsection>
            <title>See Also</title>
            <para><xref linkend="ST_SetEffectiveArea"/>, <xref linkend="ST_SimplifyVW"/></para>
          </refsection>
    </refentry>
