<refentry xml:id="ST_FrechetDistance" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	  <refnamediv>
		<refname>ST_FrechetDistance</refname>

		<refpurpose>Returns the Fréchet distance between two geometries.</refpurpose>
	  </refnamediv>

	  <refsynopsisdiv>
		<funcsynopsis>
		  <funcprototype>
			<funcdef>float <function>ST_FrechetDistance</function></funcdef>

			<paramdef><type>geometry </type>
			<parameter>g1</parameter></paramdef>

			<paramdef><type>geometry </type>
			<parameter>g2</parameter></paramdef>

			<paramdef><type>float</type>
			<parameter>densifyFrac = -1</parameter></paramdef>
		  </funcprototype>
		</funcsynopsis>
	  </refsynopsisdiv>

	  <refsection>
		<title>Description</title>

		<para>Implements algorithm for computing the Fréchet distance restricted to discrete points for both geometries, based on <link xlink:href="http://www.kr.tuwien.ac.at/staff/eiter/et-archive/cdtr9464.pdf">Computing Discrete Fréchet Distance</link>.
		The Fréchet distance is a measure of similarity between curves that takes into account the location and ordering of the points along the curves. Therefore it is often better than the Hausdorff distance. </para>
		<para>
When the optional densifyFrac is specified, this function performs a segment densification before computing the discrete Fréchet distance. The densifyFrac parameter sets the fraction by which to densify each segment. Each segment will be split into a number of equal-length subsegments, whose fraction of the total length is closest to the given fraction.
		</para>
		<para>Units are in the units of the spatial reference system of the geometries.
		</para>

		<note>
			<para>
The current implementation supports only vertices as the discrete locations. This could be extended to allow an arbitrary density of points to be used.
			</para>
		</note>
		<note>
			<para>
The smaller densifyFrac we specify, the more accurate Fréchet distance we get. But, the computation time and the memory usage increase with the square of the number of subsegments.
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>Performed by the GEOS module.</para>
		<para role="availability" conformance="2.4.0">Availability: 2.4.0 - requires GEOS &gt;= 3.7.0</para>

	  </refsection>

	  <refsection>
		<title>Examples</title>
			<programlisting>postgres=# SELECT st_frechetdistance('LINESTRING (0 0, 100 0)'::geometry, 'LINESTRING (0 0, 50 50, 100 0)'::geometry);
 st_frechetdistance
--------------------
   70.7106781186548
(1 row)
			</programlisting>
			<programlisting>SELECT st_frechetdistance('LINESTRING (0 0, 100 0)'::geometry, 'LINESTRING (0 0, 50 50, 100 0)'::geometry, 0.5);
 st_frechetdistance
--------------------
                 50
(1 row)
			</programlisting>

	  </refsection>
	  <refsection>
		<title>See Also</title>

		<para><xref linkend="ST_HausdorffDistance"/></para>
	  </refsection>
	</refentry>
